<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Automate everything | LexTech]]></title>
  <link href="http://alex.nederlof.com/blog/categories/automate-everything/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alex.nederlof.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-24T09:46:23+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://alex.nederlof.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Nederlof]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LaTeX build server]]></title>
    <link href="http://alex.nederlof.com/blog/2013/02/22/latex-build-server/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-22T10:58:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://alex.nederlof.com/blog/2013/02/22/latex-build-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had to work with <a href="http://www.LaTeX-project.org/">LaTeX</a> again. Although LaTeX has its perks like a proper equation editor and BibTex I don&rsquo;t like working with it for several reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>there is no proper <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WYSIWYG">WYSIWYG</a> editor that compiles while you type for OS X and the source files are hard to read by themselves</li>
<li>you have to manually configure that it compiles LaTeX, then bibtex, and then LaTeX twice</li>
<li>the horrors of positioning and loading images with all the different compilers, bounding boxes, etc.</li>
<li>the fact that they have their own <a href="http://tex.stackexchange.com/">Stack exchange Q&amp;A</a> is an indication of how arcane it is.</li>
</ol>


<p>Because the source files are so unpleasant to read, you always have to make sure you send the compiled latest version of your document to the right people. What I like about some MarkDown related projects like <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> and <a href="octopress.org">Octopress</a> is the way you can push the source to for example GitHub, and they build the site for you. I wanted that for LaTeX as well. Using a simple script I now have my own LaTeX build server. This way my colleagues and I can always see the latest version of the document in any browser so I don&rsquo;t have to think about distributing the latest version to the right people or devices.</p>

<p>The end result is nice and simple listing of the PDF, diff and log in a folder that indicates the build date:</p>

<p><img class="[End result]" src="/images/latex-build.png" title="End result" ></p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Setting it up</h3>

<p>I host my own Git server so I hooked the script as a <code>post-receive</code> script in the Git hooks directory. If you are running elsewhere you could also do it via a WebHook I guess. You need a workspace folder to checkout the project and a web folder to dump the results in. Here is the script:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/5015614.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/sh

WEBDIR=yourwebdir
WORKSPACE=your/workspace
TEX_FILE_NAME=your_file

echo
echo &quot;**** Pulling changes into Live [Hub&#39;s post-update hook]&quot;
echo

# Go to the checked-out version of repo
cd $WORKSPACE || exit
unset GIT_DIR

# Save the current commit id so we can calculate the diff
current=`git rev-parse HEAD`

# Update the latest changes in master
git pull origin master

# Compile the LaTex stuff
pdflatex -interaction=batchmode $TEX_FILE_NAME.tex &gt; /dev/null
bibtex -terse $TEX_FILE_NAME
pdflatex -interaction=batchmode $TEX_FILE_NAME.tex &gt; /dev/null
pdflatex -interaction=batchmode $TEX_FILE_NAME.tex

# Create a folder for the new build
NOW=$(date +&quot;%m-%d-%Y-%H%M&quot;)
OUT_DIR=$WEBDIR/$NOW
mkdir $OUT_DIR 

# Move the results to the output directory
cp $TEX_FILE_NAME.pdf $OUT_DIR/$TEX_FILE_NAME-$NOW-.pdf

# Make a syntax highlighted diff in the output directory
git diff $current..HEAD | pygmentize -l diff -f html -O full &gt; $OUT_DIR/diff.html

# Output the log messages to the output directory
git log $current..HEAD &gt; $OUT_DIR/log.txt

# And we&#39;re all done
exec git update-server-info
</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>I use <a href="http://pygments.org/">Pygments</a> to format the diff file and <code>pdflatex</code> to parse the LaTeX. Make sure you have these packages installed on you system.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m running Apache which gives a nice directory listing. However, it sorts the files in the wrong order. I want the most recent to be on top. Luckily this can be configured in Apache using the <code>IndexOrderDefault Descending Date</code> in your configuration.</p>

<h3>Potential improvements:</h3>

<ul>
<li>I use a static location for the work folder but you could also create a temporary folder and delete it afterwards.</li>
<li>This script only builds the master branch, you could also create a per-branch output folder system.</li>
<li>Adding <a href="http://kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/git-describe.html">git-discribe</a> to the output would be nice.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
